Green, Alice P.; Papers apap136
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Alice P. Green Papers
1960-2001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap136
1.89 cubic ft.
This collection contains records of the activities of Dr. Alice P. Green from her days as a student of criminal justice at the University at Albany, SUNY, through her career as founder and executive director of the Center for Law and Justice in Albany.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All processed items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Dr. Alice Green in May 2002. A set of DVDs containing videos of Dr. Green's interviews, press conferences, presentations, and television appearances were donated by her in May 2022. Following Dr. Green's death, her husband, Charles Touhey, donated additional materials in December 2024.
Biographical Sketch
Dr. Alice P. Green (1940-2024) was known for her work as a criminal justice activist in New York State. Born in South Carolina, Alice Green grew up a member of one of the few Black families in the small Adirondack mining town of Witherbee, New York. Her early experiences as an outsider in a predominantly European American, Catholic community had a profound affect on the woman she would become.
Dr. Green earned a BA in Social Science Education followed by an MA in Secondary Education of Social Sciences and English from the University at Albany, SUNY in 1967. As a teacher, she found herself becoming increasingly interested in her students' home lives and problems, which led to her earning a Master of Social Work from the University at Albany, SUNY in 1973. In 1979, she received an MA in Criminal Justice and she earned her PhD from the School of Criminal Justice at the University at Albany in 1983.
Dr. Green founded the Center for Law and Justice in 1985 and served as executive director of the Center for many years. The Center for Law and Justice is a non-profit community organization that monitors criminal justice activities, provides legal assistance and criminal justice advocacy, organizes efforts to change social policy and empowers poor people and people of color.
Prior to the creation of The Center for Law and Justice, Dr. Green was Legislative Director for the New York Civil Liberties Union. Governor Mario Cuomo appointed her to the Citizens Policy and Complaint Review Council of the New York State Commission on Corrections in 1985. In 1986, Governor Cuomo appointed her to the position of Deputy Commissioner for the New York State Division of Probation and Correctional Alternatives.
From 1975 through 1979, Dr. Green served as the Executive Director of Trinity Institution, a youth and family services center in Albany's South End neighborhood. During her time as director, she founded the South End Scene in 1977, one of the longest-running Black newspapers in Albany, New York.
In 1998, Dr. Green was running mate to Al "Grandpa" Lewis on the Green Party ticket for Lieutenant Governor of New York State. Her platform as a Green Party candidate was marked by her personal, progressive approach to criminal justice. This includes protesting the death penalty and life without parole prison sentences as well as encouraging law enforcement to make white-collar crime its number one priority. While unsuccessful in gaining the governorship, the Greens achieved their goal of receiving over 50,000 votes, which gave the party ballot status. Dr. Green was also a candidate for mayor of Albany in 2005.
Dr. Green was a published author of several books, articles and essays. These included her memoir "Outsider: Stories of Growing Up Black in the Adirondacks" (2023), "We Who Believe in Freedom: Activism and the Struggle for Social Justice," which explored police accountability, criminal justice and prison reform (2021) and "Law Never Here: A Social History of African American Responses to Issues of Crime and Justice" which she co-authored with Dr. Frankie Bailey.
Dr. Green was married to her husband, Charles Touhey, for 52 years and the couple lived in Albany during their marriage. She had two children and three grandchildren. She was honored with numerous awards for her efforts to bring change to the criminal justice system and to people of color in New York State. These included the Citizen Laureate Award from the University at Albany; distinguished Alumna Award from Rockefeller College, University at Albany; Service Award from the Albany Chapter of the NAACP; Woman of the Year Award from the YWCA; the Founder's Award and Community Service Award from the Scene Newspaper; the Community Service Award from the Albany Social Justice Center; Tile Service Award from the Israel AME Church in Albany; Shaker and Mover Award from the National Organization for Women; Black Solidarity Award from Prisoners of Auburn; Distinguished Service Award from the Prisoners of Green Haven; New York State Bar Association Public Service Medal; Victor A. Lord Courage of Convictions Award; Certificate of Recognition from the Lifers' Committee, Shawangunk Correctional Facility; and the Community Service Award from the Walls Temple AME Zion Church.
Scope and Contents
The collection is particularly strong in following Alice Green's appearances in the media in the 1980s and 1990s. The media references not only follow Dr. Green's professional career, but also highlight her activities as a fervent protestor and activist for the rights of prisoners, in attempts to repeal the Rockefeller Drug Laws and as a member of a police watchdog group in Albany. Her speeches and writings further serve to support her stance on these and other issues of the time. All news clippings have been photocopied onto acid-free paper for preservation purposes.
The collection follows the progress of the book Law Never Here: A Social History of African American Responses to Issues of Crime and Justice, which Dr. Green co-wrote with Dr. Frankie Bailey, from the initial proposals and outlines through its reviews and appearances in catalogs.
The collection also contains information on Dr. Green's bid for Lieutenant Governor on the Green Party ticket in New York State in 1998. While Alice Green's role in the 1998 election is the central focus of this series, it also provides information on the Green Party, their opponents in the election, and information about Dr. Green's running mate, Al "Grandpa" Lewis, who is best known for his role as Grandpa Munster on the 1960s television series, The Munsters. The only non-paper items in the collection are found in the Campaign Materials series, in the form of campaign buttons and a key chain.
While the correspondence series is not particularly large, it is here that letters of interest are found from Secretary of State, New York Senator, and former First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton, former mayor of Albany, New York, Thomas Whalen III, and comedian Richard Pryor.
There is a small amount of information present concerning her personal and family life, particularly relating to her husband, Charles Touhey, her son, John Green, and her hobby as an amateur runner. Among these items is Johnnie Cochran's autograph on a menu from a dinner of the One Hundred Black Men of Albany, New York.
The collection is lacking in information about Dr. Green's early career. There is very little about her education, her early days in the Albany chapter of the NAACP and her time as executive director of the Trinity Institution. The correspondence series is rather sparse, as well.
The M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives also holds the manuscript collection of the Center for Law and Justice (APAP-072), founded by Dr. Green in 1985. This collection provides valuable information about Dr. Green's work with the center. The Department's holdings also include issues of the South End Scene or Scene from July 1978 through July 1985 on microfilm. The microfilm is available for use in the Department. A manuscript collection for the NAACP, Albany Branch (APAP-074) is also available at the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Publicity, 1965-2001
Series 2 - Writings and Publications, 1976-2001
Series 3 - Speeches and Appearances, 1983-2001
Series 4 - Correspondence, 1960-2001
Series 5 - Campaign Materials, 1998
Series 6 - Personal Ephemera, circa 1960-2000
Series 1, 3, and 4 are arranged chronologically; Series 5 and 6 are arranged by subject. Series 2 is arranged by subject with the exception of subseries 2, which is arranged chronologically.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred one monograph: We Who Believe in Freedom: Activism and the Struggle for Social Justice, a memoir by Alice P. Green to the book division of Special Collections. It will be catalogued and included in the University Library Catalog.
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Public Servants; Ethnic Groups; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Albany, New York; Crime and race--United States--History.; Discrimination in criminal justice administration United States History; Governors New York (State) Election; Albany (N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Newsletters; Research Notes; Contracts; Newspapers; Speeches; Programs (documents); Correspondence; Photographs; Ephemera; Posters; Audiocassettes; Green, Alice P., 1946-; Lewis, Al, 1923-2006; Bailey, Frankie Y.; Center for Law and Justice; The South End Scene; Trinity Institution; Greens/Green Party USA; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Albany Branch; New York Civil Liberties Union
- Publicity, 1965-2001; 1; 0.49 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series is made up almost entirely of news clippings with reference to Dr. Green. Loose clippings have been photocopied onto acid-free paper for preservation, while shorter newsletters have been kept in their entirety. The collection begins sparsely in the mid-1960s and becomes increasingly dense as Dr. Green furthers her career and becomes better known in the Capital District. While the collection covers a wide variety of newspaper mentions about Dr. Green and her actions, highlights include her role as chair of the NAACP's Legal Redress Committee, during which she became involved in high-profile murder and race relations cases in 1984 and 1985; her part as a founder and member of a police watchdog group in Albany from 1986 through 1990; and her much-publicized protests at the annual Martin Luther King, Jr. Day events hosted by Governor Pataki from 1995 through 1999. As a high-profile criminologist in Albany, Dr. Green is often consulted on justice and civil liberties issues as they touch the Capital District. Some of the news clippings do not mention Dr. Green directly but are related to issues and activities she was directly involved in. The series also contains certificates and awards granted to Dr. Green and the programs and announcements that accompanied these honors. The oversized box contains a folder of materials from this series.
  - News Clippings, 1965; 1969 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, 1979 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1982 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 4)
  - News Clippings, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 6)
  - News Clippings, January-June 1985 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, July-December 1985 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 8)
  - News Clippings, January-June 1986 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, July-December 1986 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 11)
  - News Clippings, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 12)
  - News Clippings, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 13)
  - News Clippings, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 14)
  - News Clippings, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 15)
  - News Clippings, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 17)
  - News Clippings, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 18)
  - News Clippings, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 19)
  - News Clippings, January-June 1996 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 20)
  - News Clippings, July-December 1996 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 21)
  - News Clippings, January-February 1997 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 22)
  - News Clippings, March-December 1997 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 23)
  - News Clippings, January-June 1998 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 24)
  - News Clippings, July-December 1998 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 25)
  - News Clippings, January-June 1999 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 26)
  - News Clippings, July-December 1999 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 27)
  - News Clippings, January-June 2000 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 28)
  - News Clippings, July-December 2000 (Box 1 (1-Publicity), Folder 29)
  - News Clippings, January-March 2001 (Box 2 (1-Publicity), Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, April-December 2001 (Box 2 (1-Publicity), Folder 2)
  - Certificates and Awards, 1981-2001 (Box 2 (1-Publicity), Folder 3)
  - Honors and Awards Programs, ca. 1980; 1983; 1985; 1987; 1989 (Box 2 (1-Publicity), Folder 4)
  - Honors and Awards Programs, 1990; 1994-1995; 1998-99 (Box 2 (1-Publicity), Folder 5)
  - Honors and Awards Programs, 2000-2001 (Box 2 (1-Publicity), Folder 6)
  - Color copy of Middletown, NY Times Herald Record featuring a photograph of Alice Green, March 7, 1995 (Oversized 1)
  - Albany Times Union Supplement "100 Women of Excellence", June 14, 2000 (Oversized 1)
- Writings and Publications, 1976-2001; 2; 0.58 cubic ft.
  Arranged by subject.
  This series consists of both published and unpublished writings of Dr. Green. The series includes many handwritten notes and outlines, particularly in reference to Law Never Here.
  - Law Never Here, 1994-2001; 2.1; 0.22 cubic ft.
    This sub-series consists of material surrounding the publication of the book Law Never Here: A Social History of African American Responses to Issues of Crime and Justice, which Dr. Green co-wrote with Dr. Frankie Bailey, published in 1999. The series includes publishing information, materials used in the writing of the book, publicity materials and finally, book reviews and mentions of the book.
    - Proposal, ca. 1994 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 7)
    - Contract, 1995 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 8)
    - Prospectus, ca. 1995 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 9)
    - Notes and Outlines, 1994-1997 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 10)
    - Research Materials, 1995-1998 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 11)
    - Publishing Information, 1995-1998 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 12)
    - Catalogs, 1998, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 13)
    - Publishers' Copies Letters, 1994-1999 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 14)
    - Promotional Appearances, 1999-2001 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 15)
    - Promotional Materials, 1995-2000 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 16)
    - Book Reviews, 1999, 2000 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 17)
    - Mentions, 1996, 1997 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 18)
    - Royalties Statement, 1999 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 19)
    - Other Collaborations with Dr. Frankie Bailey, 1996, 1997; 2000 (Box 2 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 20)
  - The South End Scene, 1976-1991; 2.2; 0.2 cubic ft.
    This sub-series contains issues of The South End Scene, a newspaper Dr. Green founded in 1976 as Executive Director of the Trinity Institution in Albany. Alice Green's writing, most often in the form of editorials, is found throughout these newspapers. The first available issue, dated 1976, is in newsletter form.This sub-series does not represent the entirety of The South End Scene. These are original copies. There are photocopies of each issue in the collection available for use by researchers in addition to microfilm for issues published between July 1978 and July 1985 in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives Microforms Collection.
    - Vol. 1 No. 3, Newsletter, 1976 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 1)
    - Vol. 1 No. 1, (3 copies), November 1977 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 2)
    - Vol. 1 No. 2, December 1977 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 3)
    - Vol. 2 No. 1, (3 copies), January 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 4)
    - Vol. 2 No. 2, (2 copies), February 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 5)
    - Vol. 2 No. 3, (2 copies), March 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 6)
    - Vol. 2 No. 5, (2 copies), May 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 7)
    - Vol. 2 No. 6, June 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 8)
    - Vol. 2 No. 7, July 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 9)
    - Vol. 2 No. 8, (2 copies), August 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 10)
    - Vol. 2 No. 8 (sic), September 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 11)
    - Vol. 2 No. 10, (2 copies), October 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 12)
    - Vol. 2 No. 11, October 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 13)
    - Vol. 2 No. 12), December 1978 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 14)
    - Vol. 3 No. 1, (2 copies), January 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 15)
    - Vol. 3 No. 2, (3 copies), February 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 16)
    - Vol. 3 No. 2 (sic), (3 copies), March 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 17)
    - Vol. 3 No. 4, (2 copies), April 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 18)
    - Vol. 3 No. 5, (3 copies), May 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 19)
    - Vol. 3 No. 5 (sic), July 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 20)
    - Vol. 3 No. 5 (sic), (2 copies), August 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 21)
    - Vol. 3 No. 9, (2 copies), September 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 22)
    - Vol. 3 No. 10, (2 copies), October 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 23)
    - Vol. 3 No. 12, (2 copies), December 1979 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 24)
    - Vol. 5 (sic) No. 1, (2 copies), January 1980 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 25)
    - Vol. 4 No. 1, February 1980 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 26)
    - Vol. 5 No. 2, February 1981 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 27)
    - Vol. 10 No. 5, May 1986 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 28)
    - Vol. 15 No. 10, October 1991 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 29)
    - Vol. 15 No. 11, November 1991 (Box 3 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1981-2001; Undated; 2.3; 0.16 cubic ft.
    - News Clippings, 1981-1987; 1989 (Box 4 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 1)
    - News Clippings, 1991, 1992; 1994-1999 (Box 4 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 2)
    - News Clippings, 2000, 2001 (Box 4 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 3)
    - Journal Writings, 1989; 1993; 1998 (Box 4 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 4)
    - "Case Studies on the Impact of Separation Due to Incarceration on Black Families", 1983 (Box 4 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 5)
    - Personal Narratives by Dr. Green, Undated (Box 4 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, 1988; 1990; Undated (Box 4 (2-Writings and Publications), Folder 7)
- Speeches and Appearances, 1983-2001; 3; 0.31 cubic ft.
  This series consists of both the programs and advertisements for appearances by Alice Green, as well as the text and notes of the speeches she gave at some of these events. The speeches are unpublished and many of the notes and outlines are handwritten, and therefore, it is difficult to determine the date or event at which they may have been delivered. The series includes one audio cassette of the address Dr. Green delivered at the Albany Academy's 1985 commencement. Alice Green's son, John A. Green, was a graduate of this class. A folder in the oversized box contains posters for events at which Dr. Green spoke.
  - Speeches and Appearances, 1983-1986; 1989 (Box 4 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 8)
  - Albany Academy Commencement Speech Program and Audio Cassette, 1985 (Box 4 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 9)
  - Speeches and Appearances, 1990; 1994, 1995 (Box 4 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 10)
  - Speeches and Appearances, 1996 (Box 4 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 11)
  - Speeches and Appearances, 1997 (Box 4 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 12)
  - Speeches and Appearances, 1998 (Box 4 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 13)
  - Speeches and Appearances, 1999 (Box 4 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 14)
  - Speeches and Appearances, 2000 (Box 5 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 1)
  - Speeches and Appearances, 2001 (Box 5 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 2)
  - Speeches and Appearances, Undated (Box 5 (3-Speeches and Appearances), Folder 3)
  - Posters for Events, 1987; 1989; 1995; 2000 (Oversized 1)
- Correspondence, 1960-2001; 4; 0.13 cubic ft.
  This series consists of both personal and professional correspondence. The majority of the correspondence was received by Dr. Green, although there are a few copies of outgoing letters. Highlights of this series include a letter from former Albany mayor, Thomas M. Whalen, III (1987), a letter from Richard Pryor concerning the Center for Law and Justice (1995) and a note from Hillary Rodham Clinton thanking Dr. Green for an inscribed copy of Law Never Here (1999). A folder in the oversized box contains correspondence with attached legal-sized documents and cards made out of construction paper.
  - Correspondence, 1960; 1977 (Box 5 (4-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1985 (Box 5 (4-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 5 (4-Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1997 (Box 5 (4-Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 5 (4-Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 5 (4-Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 5 (4-Correspondence), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box 5 (4-Correspondence), Folder 11)
  - Letter from Former Mayor of Albany Thomas M. Whalen III, 1986 (Oversized 1)
  - Letter from Virgia B. Phoenix, 1991 (Oversized 1)
  - Construction Paper Cards, 1998 (Oversized 1)
- Campaign Materials, 1998-1999; 5; 0.27 cubic ft.
  This series consists of items relating to Alice Green's 1998 Green Party candidacy for Lieutenant Governor of New York State. The series contains documents relating to the Green Party, including newsletters, party platforms, Internet message board postings and media releases. It also includes items from the campaign trail, such as publicity materials in the form of fliers and posters, speech notes and the script of a radio advertisement. One campaign leaflet has been autographed by Alice Green's running mate, Al "Grandpa" Lewis. There are a few post-election items, including the results of the election. All news clippings in this series have been photocopied onto acid-free paper for preservation purposes. The oversized box contains a folder for this series that holds a voter's guide; Green Party newsletter and vote canvassing papers. Also in the oversized box is an envelope containing non-paper campaign materials, such as buttons and nametags.
  - Position Papers, 1998 (Box 6 (5-Campaign Materials), Folder 1)